またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
Sensei!
先生
Nyanko-sensei!
ニャンコ先生
Geez, where'd he go?
全く どこいったんだよ
いってててて
He said there was some shortcut through Nanatsujiya,
七辻屋に行く抜け道があるとか言って
道らしい道なんてないじゃないか
but there isn't even anything that looks like a road.
いい天気だな
The weather's nice.
Autumn Banquet
I told that darn Natsume to follow me,
夏目のやつめ しっかり付いて来いって言ったのに
しっかりはぐれておってからに
and now he's gone.
All right.
仕方ない 五秒ぐらい待ってやるか
I'll wait five seconds for him.
一
One, two,
二
三
three...
いって
なん 猫か 脅かすなよ
Oh, a cat?
Don't scare me.
Huh?
あれ このぶさ猫 確か夏目ん家の
Isn't this Natsume's fat cat?
Was it Nyan Nyan-sensei?
ニャンニャン先生だっけか
ニャンニャン先生 大丈夫か
Are you okay, Nyan Nyan-sensei?
ニャンニャン
Nyan Nyan...
なんか恥ずかしい名前だな
That's a pretty embarrassing name.
Let's go with Ponta.
ポンタでいいか
Hey, Ponta, wake up!
おい ポンタ 起きろ
Come on, Ponta!
こら ポンタ
It's Nyanko-sensei!
ニャンコ先生だ アホ
Aren't you Tanuma?
お前 確か田沼とか言ったな
アホのくせに なかなかやるではないか
You're pretty good for an idiot.
The...
The?
The cat talked.
猫が 喋った
D-Damn.
し しまった
お前 まだ夏目から私の正体を
You haven't heard about me from Natsume yet?
So, you're a Youkai, Ponta?
妖怪なのか ポンタ
It's Nyanko-sensei!
ニャンコ先生だ
You're not a Youkai?
妖怪じゃないのか
There's a big difference! I'm a very high being.
大きく分ければそうだが
私はとても高貴な存在だ
Don't compare me to those Ayakashi.
そこらの妖どもと一緒にす するな
This is my first time.
初めてだ
This is my first time talking to a Youkai.
妖怪と話したのは 初めてだよ 俺
That's right, you can't see us properly.
なるほど お前はちゃんと見える訳ではなかったな
So, that's why Natsume didn't tell you about me?
だから夏目も私のことを話していなかったのか
You wouldn't be much help anyway.
役に立つ訳でもないからな
えっ そうか
I see...
Maybe you're right.
そうかもしれないな
What are you to Natsume?
お前は夏目の何なんだ
His sensei!
先生だ
Natsume is my follower.
夏目は私の子分なのだ
Follower?
子分
You're not treating him badly, are you?
お前 夏目に嫌な思いをさせたりしてないどろうな
What do you mean?
どういう意味だ
Any way you look at it, you're more like the follower.
どうみても 子分はお前の方だ
脅しでもかけてるんじゃないのか
Are you threatening him?
Damn fool! I won't let you say what you want!
こいつめ 言わせておけば
私の正体を知られたからには 証拠隠滅せねばなるまい
Now that you've seen what I really am,
I'll have to destroy the evidence!
I'll swallow you who-
いただきまー
What are you doing, sensei?
何やってんだ 先生
N-Natsume?
な 夏目
Why's that cat with you?
あの猫 どうしてお前と
先生は用心棒みたいなもんで
He's something like a bodyguard.
Natsume,
夏目
話したくなきゃ 別にいいんだ
if you don't want to talk about it, it's okay.
いや そうじゃなくて
No, that's not it.
いろいろ複雑だから なんて説明したらいいか
It's pretty complex, so I'm not sure how to explain it all.
Ah, well, it's not like I wanted to hide it from you.
その 別に田沼に隠したい訳じゃ
No, that's not it.
いや 違う
ごめん 本当は隠していたかったんだ
I actually was hiding it.
田沼とは 普通に話したかったし
I wanted to talk with you normally.
That's why I didn't want to put you through anything miserable.
だから嫌な思いをさせたりとかは
Are you in a miserable situation?
嫌な思いをしてるのか
Look, Natsume! I caught a big one!
夏目 見ろ 立派なのが捕れたぞ
Look, look!
No, not really.
いや そうでもない
うん 何だ
What was that?
ああ 祭りだよ 今夜あるんだ
Ah, it's a festival.
They're holding one tonight.
お 秋祭りか
A fall festival?
では行って見よう 夏目
All right, let's go take a look, Natsume.
まだ準備中だって
They're still setting it up.
準備でもかまわん さあ行くぞ
I don't care, let's go!
ああ こら
Hey, wait, sensei!
待てよ 先生
The temple is on my way home, so I'll tag along.
神社なら 帰り道だから 付き合うよ
そうか
Okay.
Oh, it's not open yet?
なんだ まだか
I told you they were still setting up.
だから準備中だって言ったじゃないか
I thought the street stands might've been open already.
露天ぐらいやっているかと思ったのだ
Natsume-kun!
夏目君
笹田
Sasada.
What's up? It hasn't begun yet.
どうしたの まだ始まってないのに
Is someone you know here?
知り合いでもいるの
いや そう言う訳じゃないんだけど
No, that's not it.
Are you helping out?
手伝ってるの
Yeah, I was asked to.
そうなの ちょっと頼まれちゃって
I know!
分かった
They're here, aren't they?
いるんでしょう ここに
いる 何が
They're here? What is?
Don't play dumb.
とぼけないで
I heard they gather where it's really lively.
こういう賑やかな場所には 集まりやすいって聞いたことがあるわ
You're still saying that?
まだ言ってるのか
Well, it is true.
まあ 確かに いっぱいいるけど
There are a lot of them.
I'm right, aren't I? What kinds are there?
当たりね どんなのがいるの
Jun-chan!
純ちゃん
Sorry, but could you take this to the front of the shrine?
悪いけど これ拝殿に運んでちょうだい
Okay!
はーい
You.
あなた
あれ 拝殿へお願い
Please take that to the shrine.
Me?
俺が
Hurry up, I'm in the middle of a conversation.
早く あたしは話の途中なの
She asked you though.
頼まれたのお前だろう
Don't talk back to the class rep.
クラス委員に口答えしない
クラス違うんだけど
We're in difference classes though.
I'll go then.
じゃあ 俺が行くよ
You can't go.
夏目君はだめよ
純ちゃん
Jun-chan?
This person will be going!
今この人が行きまーす
Hey, hey!
Quickly!
急いで
Just wait a bit! I'll be right back!
ちょっと待ってて すぐ戻るから
よし 今のうち
Now's our chance.
だな
Yeah.
I'm sure Natsume will come to the festival.
お祭りならきっと夏目も来るぞ
What's with you?
なんだ お前
You came as a fox?
今日は狐のまんまかよ
Hold it!
ちょっと待った
Stop!
止めて
You did it now, you rascally fox!
やったな この小狐
え ち 違うよ
N-No, it wasn't me!
僕じゃないよ
You know,
俺たちの姿はな
humans can't see us.
人間には見えないんだな
ひどい
That's mean!
I just prepared those!
せっかく準備したってのに
この野郎 許さねぇ
I won't let you go!
違う違う 僕じゃない
Ah, no, no! It wasn't me!
Stop struggling!
暴れるな この
N-Natsume! Help me, Natsume!
夏目
助けて 夏目
Natsume?
ちょっと乱暴すぎやしないか
Aren't you being a bit too rough?
Who are you?
なんだ お前は
This has nothing to do with you! Get lost!
関係ねぇだろう 引っ込んでろ
この狐がやったのを見たのか
Did you see the fox do it?
No, I didn't.
いや 見ちゃいねぇけど
But he's the only one around here!
ここにはこいつしかいねぇだろう
Looks like it was the wind.
どうやら 風のようだな
手を放せ
Let go.
こいつ見えてるぞ
He can see us!
化けもんだ
He's a monster!
はい 麦茶
Here's some barley tea.
Ah, thanks.
悪い
It's so empty here that it's almost surprising, huh?
びっくりするほど何もないだろう
え ああ いや
Ah, no.
It's about time.
ちょうど時間だな
Look at the corner of the ceiling.
あの天井の隅
The ceiling?
天井
へえ きれいだな
It's pretty.
だろう
Right?
池の反射か
The pond's reflection, huh?
Look.
ほら
There isn't a pond in the backyard.
庭に池なんてないんだ
So, I think only we can see the water reflection on the ceiling.
だからたぶん 天井の水門は 俺たちにしか見えないんだと思う
What's wrong?
どうした
Ah, it's nothing.
ああ いや
そうだな 不思議だな
Yeah, it's strange.
So, Tanuma can't see the pond.
田沼には 池が見えないんだ
どうした
What?
I forgot him.
忘れてきた
He got away...
逃げられちゃった
Natsume-kun's fat cat.
夏目君とこのブサイクちゃん
If he's here, then Natsume will come back.
この子がいれば 夏目君は戻ってくるわ
All right!
よし
Excuse me, do you have any rope? Oh, and as tough as possible.
すみません 紐ありませんか
なるべくごついやつ
いや 夏目 それ背骨ではない
No, Natsume, those aren't my whiskers.
肩甲骨だよ 止めろ
It's my cheek.
Stop.
Thank you!
ありがとう
You're welcome.
どういたしまして
So, you can understand me.
僕の言葉が分かるんだね
Yeah.
まあね
Do you know Natsume?
夏目 知ってる
え いや
No.
I see. Natsume can understand me too.
そう 夏目も僕の言葉が分かるんだ
Did you come to meet him?
キミは その人に会いに来たのかい
Yeah! I'm sure he'll come.
うん きっと来るはずだから
I see, I hope you'll meet him.
そうか 会えるといいね
Yeah! Well, thank you!
それじゃあ ありがとう
Bye!
さよなら
Hiiragi.
柊 あの子に付いていてやれ
Follow him.
Yes.
はい
Forgive my tardiness.
遅くなりました
How careless of me!
不覚を取ったわ
Calm down a bit.
少し落ち着きなさい
貴志君 お祭りに直接行くなら そう言ってくれればいいのに
Takashi-kun could've told us he'd be going straight to the festival.
He's not a child.
貴志は子供じゃないんだぞ
But, if he's in an accident...
でも もし事故にでも遭ってたら
You worry too much.
心配性だな
Nyangoro will come tell us if that happens.
その時は ニャン五郎が知らせにきてくれるさ
Don't joke around, geez...
ふざけないでください もう
How long has it been since Takashi came here?
貴志が来て どのぐらい経つんだっけ
I'm sure he's gone through a lot of tough things,
今まで辛い思いをして来たんだろうが
but he's too considerate.
気を使いすぎなんだよ あいつは
But with him going out on his own like this, I am put at ease.
このぐらい勝手をしてくれた方が 俺は楽だな
Being too considerate of each other isn't being a family.
お互い気を使い合ってるなんて
家族じゃないだろう
But...
でも
We were a bit too early.
まだちょっと早かったね
Yeah.
そうね
あら
What? Someone dropped it?
なんだ 落し物か
I'll go return it!
あたし届けてくる
A dropped item?
落し物ね
All right, I'll hold on to it.
わかりました 預かっておきます
Thank you.
よろしくお願いします
ご苦労様
Someone dropped something.
あの これ 落し物だそうです
Okay.
はい
Kitty! What's wrong? Did they catch you?
猫ちゃん どうしたの 捕まっちゃったの
Did you do something bad?
なんか悪いことしたの
All right, I'll save you!
よし 民子が助けてあげる
It got away!
逃げられた
Could you help me for a bit?
ちょっと手伝って
Ah, okay.
はい
Ponta's not here.
いないな ポンタ
Yeah.
そうだな
Ponta?
ポンタ
Ah, sorry. It's nothing.
ごめん こっちの話
How about we split up and look?
手分けして 探してみるか
Sorry, but will you?
悪いな
そうしてくれるか
Yeah.
よし
I don't see your pouch.
見当たらんな 巾着袋
You can't remember where you dropped it?
どこで落としたか 見当はつかないのか
Is what's inside so important?
そんなに大事なものが入っていたのか
Yeah, it's really important.
うん すっごく大事なの
I see.
そうか
Let's search over there.
もっと向こうも探してみよう
Where'd sensei go?
どこ行ったんだよ 先生
あれ
Hey, Natsume! So you came!
おお 夏目 やっぱ来てたか
Hey, did you see Nyan-
No, did you see my cat?
な ニャンコ先
いや 家の猫を見なかったか
That fat cat?
あの豚猫 見なかったけど
Nope.
I see.
そうか
Did it run away?
逃げたのか
Yeah.
まあな じゃあ
See you.
Yeah.
Here you go.
はいよ お待ち
Ah, thanks.
はい
あれ
Where's my taiyaki, mister?
おっちゃん 俺の回転焼きは
Huh? I just gave it to you.
今渡したろう
I didn't get anything!
もらってないよ
I did, just pay up.
渡したよ 代金払いな
I'm not going to pay for what I didn't get!
もらってないのに 払えるかよ
What'd you say?!
何だと
え あ いや
Ah, uh, no...
Ah, how much was it?
あのー おいくらでしょう
What's he doing?
何をやってるんだ あいつ
Is that it?
あれか
Yeah.
Just what's inside it?
一体何が入っているんだ
Medicine.
薬
Medicine?
It's medicine that allows me to be human for a while.
ちょっとの間だけ 人間になれる薬なの
I'll cause Natsume trouble if I'm in my animal form.
獣の姿だと 夏目に迷惑かけちゃうから
I see, so that's how it is.
なるほど そういうことか
All right, I'll go and...
よし では私が行って
Hey!
あ おい
You came here because of the smell of food, didn't you, little fox?
食べ物の匂いに誘われて来たのね 狐君ったら
You can't have it though!
だめよ しっしっ
Hey!
こら ちょ
That's not it!
違うよ
Stop!
止めて
Natsume!
夏目
Natsume-kun!
夏目君
It sneaked in?
入り込んだのか
え ああ そうなのよ
Yeah.
I see.
そうか じゃあ 山へ逃がしてくるよ
I'll let it go in the mountains then.
Yeah, thanks.
うん ありがとう
Wait, I'll go too!
待って あたしも行く
Hey!
おい
The pot's boiling.
鍋 煮立ってるぞ
え いけない
Oh no!
That's strange, I'm sure I lowered the fire.
おかしいな 火弱めたはずなのに
Thanks!
ありがとう
It's dangerous if you're in a crowd of people with that form.
その姿で人ごみに来たら危ないじゃないか
I'm sorry, but...!
ごめんなさい でも
Well...
だって
I brought it for you.
持って来てやったぞ
You're...
君は
Thanks!
ありがとう
If you're here, Hiiragi, then Natori-san is here too?
柊 君がいるっていうことは
名取さんもここに
Yes.
まあな 人と会っている
He's meeting someone now.
He asked you to watch him?
あの人に頼まれて この子と
You're being careless talking to me in such a crowded area.
無防備だな
人気の多い場所で私のようなものと話していると
They'll find you creepy.
気味悪がられるぞ
I don't mind,
構わないよ
because I can see you.
だって 俺には見えてるんだから
You're too kind.
お人好しなやつめ
Are you that little fox from before?
お前
もしかして さっきの小狐か
He's fine.
この人は大丈夫だよ
I'm finally free.
やっと自由になった
Damn that Natsume, he didn't even come to save me.
しかし夏目のやつめ 助けにもこないとは
How cruel.
なんという
Welcome back,
お帰り
fatty.
ブサイクちゃん
This area is pretty cold.
この辺りはさすがに寒いな
Yeah.
まあな でも静かだよ
It's quiet though.
Hey.
なあ
You could see the pond in my backyard, right?
夏目には 庭の池が見えたんだろう
All I can see are the shadows on the ceiling.
俺には天井の影しか見えなかったけど
Does Touko-san know you can see these things?
塔子さんは知ってるのか
お前が見えるってこと
No.
いや
You don't believe in them?
信じてないのか あの人達のこと
That's not it.
そうじゃない
They're kind, so I'm sure they'll believe me if I tell them.
優しいから きっと 話せば受け入れてくれると思う
But, because they're kind,
でも 優しいから 今までの俺を思って
I'm sure they'll feel bad because they've cared for me so much.
きっと 心を痛めると思うんだ
It may be selfish,
自分勝手な考えかもしれないけど
but I don't like it.
それが嫌でさ
I want them to always be smiling.
あの人達には ずっと笑っていてほしいんだ
It's started.
始まったぞ
へえ 思ったより立派じゃないか
It's better than I thought.
I thought it would've been more shabby since it's the countryside.
田舎だから もっとしょぼいかと思ってた
Yeah.
What is it?
どうした
え いや
Nothing.
Sorry, I actually can't see it.
悪い 本当は見えないんだ
There's some big guy in the way.
なんかでっかい奴が邪魔で
A big guy? You mean a Youkai?
でっかいやつ
妖怪か
Yeah.
ああ でも きれいなのは分かるよ
I can tell that it's pretty though.
He's gazing at it so intently.
あいつが あんなに見惚れてるんだから
Let's walk for a bit.
少し歩こう
There might be some place so you can see too.
夏目にも 見える場所があるかもしれない
Yeah, let's go.
ああ 行こう
うわ きれい
It's so pretty!
I can see it well here.
ここなら よく見えるよ
I see, that's great.
そうか よかった
What color are the shadow fish?
あの影の魚 本物は何色なんだ
They're red.
赤だよ
Red...
赤
I see.
そうか
So, this is where you are, you heartless bastard.
ここにおったか 薄情者め
あ ニャンコ先生
Nyanko-sensei!
I can't believe you left your precious bodyguard, you...!
大事な用心棒をほったらかしにして お前という奴は
There's another one!
また上がった
I could hear the winter's footsteps approaching.
冬の足音が聞こえる 秋の夜
It's an autumn night,
but it's warm here.
でも ここは暖かい
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
夕立の雨上がりに
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.